{
  "lessonId": "lesson11",
  "lessonTitle": "Урок 11",
  "lessonDescription": " ",
  "lessonURL": "",
  "lessonItems": [
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "Does + <i>he/she/it</i> + присудок + ?",
      "startTime": "01:41"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Він говорить англійською?",
      "answer":   "Does he speak English?",
      "startTime": "02:19"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вона розуміє французьку?",
      "answer":   "Does she understand French?",
      "startTime": "2:39"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Воно (тварина) п'є воду?",
      "answer":   "Does it drink water?",
      "startTime": "03:11"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "(Ця) мама готує піцу по суботах?",
      "answer":   "Does the mum cook pizza on Saturdays?",
      "startTime": "03:23"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Джон (John) летить до Африки?",
      "answer":   "Does John fly to Africa?",
      "startTime": "03:38"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Наталі переїжджає до Словакії?",
      "answer":   "Does Natalie move to Slovakia?",
      "startTime": "03:52"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Твій тато зустрічає тебе сьогодні?",
      "answer":   [
        "Does your dad meet you today?",
        "Does your father meet you today?",
      ],
      "startTime": "04:05"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>mice</b> /maɪs/ миші<br /><b>mouse</b> /maʊs/ миша",
      "startTime": "04:14"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Кіт ловить мишей?",
      "answer":   "Does a cat catch mice?",
      "startTime": "04:17"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Він покращує англійську?",
      "answer":   "Does he improve English?",
      "startTime": "04:47"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "(Ця) жінка любить тебе?",
      "answer":   "Does the woman love you?",
      "startTime": "04:56"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>birthday</b> /ˈbɜːθ.deɪ/ день народження<br /><b>party</b> /ˈpɑː.ti/ (UK), /ˈpɑɹ.ti/ (US) вечірка, тусовка",
      "startTime": "5:48"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>us</b> /əs/ нас, нам",
      "startTime": "5:56"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ліз запрошує нас на день народження?",
      "answer":   "Does Liz invite us to a birthday party?",
      "startTime": "06:05"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Він говорить (цю) правду?",
      "answer":   "Does he say the truth?",
      "startTime": "6:35"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Дівчина отримує насолоду від цієї страви?",
      "answer":   "Does the girl enjoy this dish?",
      "startTime": "6:51"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Твій друг зазвичай телефонує тобі?",
      "answer":   "Does your boyfriend usually call you?",
      "startTime": "7:19"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вона часто говорить із ним?",
      "answer":   "Does she often talk to him?",
      "startTime": "7:44"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>neighbour</b> /ˈneɪbə/ сусід",
      "startTime": "08:08"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "(Цей) сусід сідає у таксі тут?",
      "answer":   "Does the neighbour catch the taxi here?",
      "startTime": "08:12"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>here</b> /hɪə(ɹ)/, /hɪː(ɹ)/ тут<br /><b>there</b> /ðɛə(ɹ)/, /ðɛː(ɹ)/ там",
      "startTime": "8:37"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Її брат створює вебсайт?",
      "answer":   "Does her brother create a website?",
      "startTime": "8:57"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вона займається плаванням?",
      "answer":   "Does she go swimming?",
      "startTime": "09:09"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Себастьян (Sebastian) грає у великий теніс?",
      "answer":   "Does Sebastian play lawn tennis?",
      "startTime": "09:29"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Він любить дощову погоду?",
      "answer":   "Does he like a rainy weather?",
      "startTime": "9:52"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>dance</b> /dæns/ танцювати",
      "startTime": "10:39"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Та чарівна дівчина танцює?",
      "answer":   "Does that beautiful girl dance?",
      "startTime": "10:52"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "(Той) студент вивчає Present Simple?",
      "answer":   "Does the student learn Present Simple?",
      "startTime": "11:15"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>weather</b> /ˈwɛðə/ погода",
      "startTime": "11:45"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Він чекає сонячної погоди?",
      "answer":   "Does he wait for a sunny weather?",
      "startTime": "11:47"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "(Цей) хлопець подорожує за кордон?",
      "answer":   "Does the boy travel abroad?",
      "startTime": "12:01"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>cut</b> /kʌt/, різати, вирізати",
      "startTime": "12:22"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Він ріже хліб?",
      "answer":   "Does he cut bread?",
      "startTime": "12:27"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Він хоче випити вина?",
      "answer":   "Does he want to drink wine?",
      "startTime": "12:43"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>writer</b> /ˈɹaɪ.təɹ/ письменник",
      "startTime": "13:02"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Письменник пише книги?",
      "answer":   "Does a writer write books?",
      "startTime": "13:04"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>nurse</b> /nɜːs/ медична сестра",
      "startTime": "13:27"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Медична сестра допомагає людям?",
      "answer":   "Does a nurse help people?",
      "startTime": "13:38"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Він показує гарний результат?",
      "answer":   "Does he show a good result?",
      "startTime": "14:01"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Твій батько відкриває новий центр?",
      "answer":   [
        "Does your dad open a new centre?",
        "Does your father open a new centre?",
      ]
      "startTime": "14:11"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "Does <i>з'їдає</i> закінчення <s>s</s> у дієслова:<br />The girl dances ⇨ dance<s>s</s> ⇨ Does the girl dance?",
      "startTime": "15:11"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Він часто пише мені повідомлення",
      "answer":   "He often writes me messages",
      "startTime": "17:08"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Я люблю його",
      "answer":   "I love him",
      "startTime": "17:43"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>prompt</b> /pɹɒmpt/ підказка",
      "startTime": "18:00"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Він не користується моєю підказкою",
      "answer":   "He doesn't use my prompt",
      "startTime": "18:08"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Він знає все?",
      "answer":   "Does he know everything?",
      "startTime": "18:35"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>reporter</b> /ɹɪˈpɔːtə/ репортер<br /><b>interview</b> /ˈɪntəvjuː/ інтерв'ю",
      "startTime": "18:55"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Репортер бере інтерв'ю в людей",
      "answer":   "The reporter interviews people",
      "startTime": "19:02"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ти дякуєш її сестрі?",
      "answer":   "Do you thank her sister?",
      "startTime": "19:38"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Восени йде сніг?",
      "answer":   "Does it snow in autumn?",
      "startTime": "19:58"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>little</b> /ˈlɪtəl/ малий<br /><b>science</b> /ˈsaɪəns/ наука<br /><b>fiction</b> /ˈfɪk.ʃən/ художня література",
      "startTime": "20:25"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Мій маленький брат не дивиться наукову фантастику",
      "answer":   "My little brother doesn't watch science fiction",
      "startTime": "20:34"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Її маленька сестра витратила всі (ці) гроші?",
      "answer":   "Does her little sister spend all the money?",
      "startTime": "21:03"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Я не знаю (цього)",
      "answer":   "I don't know this",
      "startTime": "21:23"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вона не грає у волейбол гарно",
      "answer":   "She doesn't play volleyball very well",
      "startTime": "22:03"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Люк (Luke) миє машину регулярно",
      "answer":   "Luke washes his car regularly",
      "startTime": "22:13"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Він купує торт на день народження?",
      "answer":   "Does he buy a birthday cake?",
      "startTime": "22:24"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ми зазвичай їздимо на роботу машиною",
      "answer":   "We usually go to work by car",
      "startTime": "22:37"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ти часто її бачиш?",
      "answer":   "Do you often see her?",
      "startTime": "22:48"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Подивись на цю гітару!",
      "answer":   "Look at this guitar!",
      "startTime": "23:04"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вона (it) звучить чудово",
      "answer":   "It sounds beautifully",
      "startTime": "23:36"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Сью (Sue) йому номер телефону",
      "answer":   "Sue doesn't give him a phone number",
      "startTime": "24:09"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Він працює наполегливо",
      "answer":   "He works very hard",
      "startTime": "24:22"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вона не вірить їм",
      "answer":   "She doesn't believe them",
      "startTime": "24:30"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ці студенти навчаються в університеті Оксфорда",
      "answer":   "These students study at Oxford University",
      "startTime": "25:20"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вона не говорить швидко",
      "answer":   "She doesn't talk very fast",
      "startTime": "25:34"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ви практикуєте англійську регулярно?",
      "answer":   "Do you practise English regularly?",
      "startTime": "25:46"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Він планує свій день?",
      "answer":   "Does he plan his day?",
      "startTime": "25:56"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>meaning</b> /ˈmiːnɪŋ/ значення",
      "startTime": "26:04"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ти знаєш значення слова",
      "answer":   "You know the meaning of the word",
      "startTime": "26:06"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Він поспішає кожного ранку",
      "answer":   "He hurries up every morning",
      "startTime": "26:34"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Ти малюєш фарбами вдома?",
      "answer":   "Do you paint at home?",
      "startTime": "26:44"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>work from home</b> працювати <b>з</b> дому",
      "startTime": "26:52"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Він працює з дому",
      "answer":   "He works from home",
      "startTime": "26:55"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "point",
      "itemText": "<b>granny</b> /ˈɡɹæni/ бабуся",
      "startTime": ":"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Твоя бабуся почувається добре?",
      "answer":   "Does your granny feel well?",
      "startTime": "26:46"
    },
    {
      "itemType": "question",
      "question": "Вони підходять один одному",
      "answer":   "They match each other",
      "startTime": "28:20"
    },
  ]
}
